Those who are taking the view through fundamentals, I think the first time I covered
Pena, we talked about options, and so I just need to do a quick overview on the composition
stores, now that we are all on the same page regarding composable APIs and how they work.
So the technique here is basically called composition or setup stores.
I explicitly left the task store in here because, as you can see here, this is an example of an
option store. And so this is actually useful context for those, especially if you were always
pure composition API and you came into view three, it's neat as I've taught workshops over
the years to see the audience change from like, I've never used composition API to people
not saying I've never used options API, like things have changed, it's kind of wild. And so
for those of you who have been pure composition API, this was kind of the elegance of the
options API. In the sense that you knew exactly where to put stuff. State goes inside of this
state key, getters, which are essentially computed, go inside of getters, and then your actions
were essentially your methods or your functions. And so that was basically all it was.
And that's one of the elements of the options API and one of the reasons it was so popular
is because it allowed people who might not be a savvy from the JavaScript perspective to still
come in and be to contribute to the code base. And so I think one of my stories I always
like to share is that I'm teaching a workshop introductory to view as back in view two,
it's not view three yet. And there's a designer who she told me, she almost didn't come to
the workshop at all because she'd only been doing like, HTML and CSS for most of her coding,
and she hadn't done that for years. And so she thought she was going to be completely way out
of her death. But she decided to stick it out. And the workshop was I think about two hours.
And by the end of it, she had a functioning view app and was able to understand the basics of
like updating the state and whatnot. And it wasn't incredibly complicated, but I think the fact
that she was able to do so speaks to, I mean, that is the power of standards and having people
being able to follow those things. And so I, you know, like any cautionary tell, I love composition
API, I love how flexible it is, but we do have to remember that we still want to try to keep
our code as, you know, maintainable, scalable as humanly possible so that it is still accessible
as much as humanly possible to our users when we can. Okay, so here, basically, what a set of
sort is, is instead of just saying, hey, look, we're going to have this defined store that's
an object that is the options. It basically just says, hey, look, we're going to have this defined
store that has this key. And this time, we're going to have a function that returns a bunch of stuff.
And so, for example, all this state, so just to keep it easy, I mean, delete this, this is state.
All this stuff in here just becomes variables. Do, do, do, one, two, const, one, two, this.
Okay, all of your getters. Well, I need to, actually, let me, let me do this first. Do, do, do,
whoop, sorry, import ref. And that's just going to grab computer well on that.
So, you storage is already done here. So, I'm just going to leave that alone so people have that to turn a different
sheet that it really doesn't look as, can I wrap this whole thing? Apparently, I can. Okay,
then, all of our getters here, which are essentially computed. So, these are ref or reactive,
your choice. Generally, I recommend ref because it's just a bit more stable.
And then, so we have one, two, let's say, okay, I'll just focus on these first const,
equals, and then we have computed. And then we don't need the state anymore because it's inherently
going to be reference, pass dot value dot length. That's it for that one. Then this one's
computed, yep, returns, task dot value dot reduce. La, la, la, la, bum, bum, then I think that
is covered. And then, we can put more, do, do, do, const dot dot dot, two, equals computed state.
Whoops, we've got one. That goes here. And then set a state dot task,
state dot value, task dot value, yep, that takes care of all the getters. And finally,
luckily, actions are actually pretty easy, because they basically are just, you know, at the function
in front of it. I need to update some of those in a second, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da, da,
function, function, function, and function. Okay, that was a lot to get through. And so then,
remember, we're back in now set up world, so this no longer exists. So honestly what I'm going to do,
I'm just going to grab all the, this, this dot tasks, do, do, do, do, do, do, do, and then we're just
going to grab them, switch them to dot value. And then what else is airing out, this dot is loading,
okay, oh wait, that's not what I want to, this dot error, that's what I want. Okay,
and then this dot, uh, we dot, uh, dot, dot, value, excellent, this dot is loading,
dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot,
and we think we're almost done.
Okay, I think that if first crilly bracket,
we have a spare crilly bracket we're very bottom, all right, woo. I could call it,
good call. And then this one, no, doesn't like it. Okay, this that update tasks just becomes
update tasks. No need for that.
Save something so funky.
Good to bottom.
This one, we don't need.
You need an extra one. Yeah, you need your closing bracket,
curl it or bracket the parenthesis and then bracket maybe,
bracket parenthesis then bracket parenthesis then bracket parenthesis.
Like this. Okay, beautiful. Yeah, all right, because we need to close this giant
thing, this loop. Yeah, yeah, okay. Woo, okay, there you go. That is everything. Now the difference
also being, right, we just switch everything over to composition API is that then you need to go
ahead and return all the things. So this is where you have to be explicit regarding the
fact that you're saying task is loading error. So now that's that. And then we have all our
getters here. I'm just moving that in. So I just see them getters. So we have what task count,
task by status, task by area, and then unique areas. Yep, then done, done, and then finally
exposing all of these. Let me just collapse them in the middle of easier and create, update,
speed, yep, and then some helper methods. Okay, let me do that. Do two actions create, update,
delete. I think those are the three. I miss something update. No, yeah, yeah, yeah, update. Great.
Finally, yep, I'll need that comment a second, and then these last helper methods. Woo, this is a
long one. All right, what do we got? Get task by ID, get a task by week, get task by ID, great, get
task, thank goodness for autocomplete, and then update task status, and then update task. Hi.
Okay. This is your setup store. You can see it's actually, it's a little robust, just because
you're setting everything manually now, right? That's what you get by doing this setup store.
But it does mean that kind of like you're seeing here, you're able to then group things by like
if you want by their like feature pieces if you really wanted. For example, like unique areas,
this one, honestly, doesn't really make a lot of sense. It's like a meta attribute of tasks.
And so if I were like fully refactoring this kind of thing, this would not probably live in here.
Because I don't see why I would want to derive all unique areas from tasks that seems like
expensive, from computation perspective. But then it's related to here, but task by area. So it's
kind of interesting. So you get to like, whereas as we saw with the options store, you have to put
it in state getters and actions like that is the order. This, you get to start thinking how you might
want to redo it. And then more importantly, there's nothing stopping you from creating composables
to make this store just more comprehensible, right? I know we talked about composables being often
shared between components, but if they help to keep your sanity as far as like making your store
shorter, making them easier to understand, that's to me as valuable in its own regard. And so it's
to me that's ultimately our goal as programmers is to build things that people can easily understand
and then maintain and update. And so whatever, by whatever tools you need to do that, that is what
ultimately I think we should do.